<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A recantation sermon preached in the gate-house at VVestminster the 30. day of Iuly 1620 In the presence of many worshipfull persons, by Iohn Harding, late Priest and Dominican Fryar. Wherein he hath declared his iust motiues which haue moued him to leaue the Church of Rome, and to vnite himselfe with the reformed Church of England, whose faith and doctrine, the ancient fathers and holy martyrs haue confirmed both by bloud and writing. Shewing herein the grose errors of Rome, in matters of faith, their corrupting the Fathers, and their present declining to some strange and future ruine.</title>
            <author>Harding, John, fl. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115165</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850384</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850384</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1274:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A recantation sermon preached in the gate-house at VVestminster the 30. day of Iuly 1620 In the presence of many worshipfull persons, by Iohn Harding, late Priest and Dominican Fryar. Wherein he hath declared his iust motiues which haue moued him to leaue the Church of Rome, and to vnite himselfe with the reformed Church of England, whose faith and doctrine, the ancient fathers and holy martyrs haue confirmed both by bloud and writing. Shewing herein the grose errors of Rome, in matters of faith, their corrupting the Fathers, and their present declining to some strange and future ruine.</title>
                  <author>Harding, John, fl. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Barnard Alsop for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop against the Counduit in Fleetestreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A recantation sermon by a Dominican Fryar.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Renunciation (Canon law) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic ex-priests --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15581:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RECANTATION SERMON PREACHED IN THE GATEHOVSE AT VVEST-<hi>minſter</hi> the 30. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1620. In the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of many worſhipfull perſons, by</hi> Iohn Harding, late Prieſt and Dominican Fryar.</p>
            <p>Wherein he hath declared his iuſt motiues which haue <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to leaue the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and to vnite himſelfe</hi> with the reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe faith and doctrine, the ancient fathers and holy <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs hane confirmed both by bloud and writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing herein the groſe errors of <hi>Rome,</hi> in matters of faith, <hi>their corrupting the Fathers, and their preſent declining</hi> to ſome ſtrange and future <hi>Ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Barnard Alſop</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop againſt the Counduit in Fleeteſtreet.</p>
            <p>1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15581:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE SIR ROBERT <hi>Nanton,</hi> Knight, chiefe Secretary to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ſtate and one of his Maieſties</hi> moſt Honorable Priuie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hath paſſed a dangerous <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> and hath recouered his former <hi>health</hi> againe, is bound in a double <hi>Obligation:</hi> The one is to bee gratefull to the <hi>Perſon</hi> by whoſe meanes he recouered his <hi>health:</hi> The other is to vſe all meanes poſsible, that thoſe which be <hi>ſick</hi> of the like <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> may by his <hi>recouery</hi> be the better: Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of our Sauior, <hi>Et tu co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſus confirma fratres tuos:</hi> And therefore right Honourable, although it be ſomewhat beſides cuſtome to make <hi>Dedications</hi> of printed <hi>Sermons;</hi> yet it is my <hi>duty</hi> to offer to your <hi>Honour</hi> the firſt fruits of my <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion:</hi> Your <hi>Honor</hi> being next and immediately vnder <hi>God</hi> the chiefe <hi>worker</hi> thereof. The which as it is a gretaer <hi>benefite</hi> then any worldly thing can afford <hi>me,</hi> ſo doth it require a fuller <hi>acknowledgement</hi> then as yet, I could at any time <hi>manifeſt:</hi> howſoeuer I haue moſt earneſtly deſiredit. In which reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer intreated by ſome of my <hi>friends</hi> to publiſh this <hi>Sermon</hi> of my <hi>Recantation,</hi> and to ſet downe to the open <hi>view</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:15581:3"/>iuſt <hi>reaſons,</hi> and ſollid <hi>grounds</hi> that moued mee there unto. I haue made hold to paſſe it vnder your <hi>Honours</hi> name, hoping by your former encouragements, of your loning acceplance. And albeit they be but my firſt <hi>Aſſayes</hi> in this kind, and therefore may chance to ſeem: but harſh, yet becauſe my deſire is only to ſet forth <hi>God;</hi> mercy towards me: your <hi>Honors</hi> louing kindneſſe ſhewed to me, And to ſtop the mouthes of ſome malicious <hi>Papiſts</hi> that rayle againſt me, I truſt that your <hi>Honour</hi> will accept of this my weake endeauour as a <hi>token</hi> of my thankefull <hi>mind,</hi> which I in all <hi>duty</hi> recommend vnto your <hi>Honours</hi> fauour, and your <hi>ſelfe</hi> and yours, in your <hi>affaires</hi> vnto the <hi>mercy,</hi> and bliſſe of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> who ever ſo aſsſiſt your <hi>Honour</hi> in all your proceedings, as that after theſe preſent toyles and troubles, your <hi>Honor</hi> may receine that happy <hi>Crowne</hi> of glory, <hi>Quam repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcit Deus diligentibus ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors euer in Chriſt Ieſus</hi> Iohn Harding,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15581:3"/>
            <head>A RECANTATION SERMON, PREACHED BY A DOMINICAN Fryar.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 119. verſe 71.</bibl> 
                  <hi>It is good for me that I have beene in trouble, for thereby I have learned thy Statutes.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De elementia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad <hi>Neronem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eneca</hi> a graue <hi>Phyloſopher,</hi> writing vnto <hi>Nero,</hi> and tracting of <hi>Cinna</hi> an ancient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and publike Rebell, hee vſeth theſe words: <hi>Periti medici vbi blanda medela non pracedat tentant contrarium.</hi> It is the vſe of good <hi>Phyſicians</hi> that when a gentle <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> doth take no place, they preſently apply a ſharper <hi>ſalue,</hi> and more bitter <hi>corraſiue:</hi> The like courſe taketh Almighty <hi>God</hi> with thoſe that bee repugnant vnto his <hi>holy</hi> will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious againſt his knowne truth, when faire meanes and louing kindnes cannot preuaile, then goeth he <hi>non allicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſed compellendo,</hi> not by alluring or enticing, them but by compelling and enforcing them, <hi>vt quod non poſsit per diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptatione</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:15581:4"/>
               <hi>ſaltem poſ sit per vim,</hi> that thoſe whom hee cannot <hi>win</hi> by louing <hi>exhortations</hi> he will bring them home by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities:</hi> For as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> an ancient Grecian ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, afflictions are our inſtructions, and extremitie is <hi>Gods</hi> opportunity. The <hi>prodigal child</hi> would not returne vn-his father vntill extremity compelled him, <hi>Manaſſes</hi> liuing in his pompe and pleaſure in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> planted groues, and ſet vp Idols againſt <hi>God</hi> and godlineſſe, but being in priſon in <hi>Babilon,</hi> and chained in a dungeon the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith, that he did turne his <hi>heart</hi> vnto the Lord his <hi>God</hi> and beſought him earneſtly: therefore ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> to all things, there is an appointed time, and a time for euery purpoſe vnder the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: <hi>God</hi> hath his time to <hi>afflict</hi> vs, that we may the more earneſtly ſeeke after him, <hi>multiplicatae ſunt infirmitates, eorum poſtea acclerauerme:</hi> as our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>ſeeke and you ſhall find?</hi> But how muſt we ſeek? it is ſaid we muſt ſeeke him by Prayer. <hi>Inuoca me in die tribulationis &amp; ego exaudiam te,</hi> call vpon me in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> being much <hi>afflicted</hi> in many of his <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> doth often call vpon the <hi>Lord,</hi> as in the 120. <hi>Pſalme ad Dominum cum tribularer clamaui:</hi> when I was in trouble I called vppon the Lord, and in the 130. <hi>Pſalme, de profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis clamaui ad te domini, domine exaudi vocem meam,</hi> out of the deepe of my heart haue I called vnto thee O <hi>Lord,</hi> O Lord heare my <hi>prayer:</hi> ſo that as <hi>proſperity</hi> doth cauſe many to forget <hi>God,</hi> and to neglect their <hi>duties</hi> towards him: ſo doth <hi>aduerſity</hi> call them <hi>home</hi> againe, and makes <hi>them</hi> more carefull to ſeeke after him, and to <hi>walke</hi> more warily in his <hi>wayes.</hi> And therefore, the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in another place of this <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſaith, <hi>Before I was in trouble I went wrong, but now haue I learned to keep thy lawes,</hi> and ſo concludeth in the ſeuenth verſe ſaying, <hi>bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt mihi quia bumili aſti me,</hi> it is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15581:4"/>good for me that I haue beene in <hi>trouble.</hi> The like may I ſay at this <hi>time</hi> right <hi>Worſhipfull</hi> and my louing <hi>auditors,</hi> it was good for mee that I haue beene in <hi>trouble,</hi> for before I was in <hi>trouble</hi> albeit I had a zeale to ſerue the <hi>Lord,</hi> yet I had not the true way and <hi>meanes</hi> to ſerue him as he ought to be ſerued: hauing liued as long time from the <hi>truth</hi> as from my <hi>country</hi> and <hi>friends,</hi> being from my firſt arriuall into this <hi>Land,</hi> deteyned in <hi>pryſon,</hi> ſequeſtred from all <hi>conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>ſociety.</hi> In this my <hi>affliction</hi> and long <hi>miſery</hi> I <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> both inſtantly and <hi>feruently</hi> to the <hi>Almighty</hi> that hee would vouhcſafe to open mine <hi>eyes, enlighten</hi> my darkenes, and incline my <hi>heart</hi> vnto his <hi>teſtimonies,</hi> that I might ſerue him in <hi>holineſſe</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe all the dayes of my life,</hi> for in him <hi>only,</hi> and for him <hi>only,</hi> I <hi>deſired</hi> to <hi>liue</hi> and <hi>dye,</hi> refol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing my <hi>ſelfe</hi> that whatſoeuer ſhall bee fall <hi>me</hi> in this <hi>life,</hi> I will eſteeme it all <hi>happineſſe,</hi> for the peace of <hi>conſcience</hi> and the glory of <hi>Gods</hi> moſt <hi>holy</hi> name.</p>
            <p>As I was thus communing with my <hi>ſoule,</hi> there came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my <hi>mind</hi> that worthy precept of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Truſt not euery</hi> Spirit, <hi>but try the</hi> Spirits, <hi>whether they bee of God or no:</hi> Likewiſe I did much ruminate and <hi>ponder</hi> with my <hi>ſelfe,</hi> the place of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> where he ſaith; to the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> If they ſpeake not according to this Word, <hi>It is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> Whence I did gather, that all <hi>Seruices</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable before <hi>God:</hi> For <hi>Faith</hi> commeth by <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> of the word of <hi>God:</hi> ſo that if they ſpeake not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this <hi>Word</hi> it is rather <hi>fancy,</hi> then <hi>faith,</hi> humane <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> then Gods <hi>inſtitutions,</hi> and conſequently condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in the 15. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> where he expreſly reprooued the <hi>Commandements</hi> and <hi>traditions</hi> of men. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> reiecteth as <hi>Baſtard</hi> ſlippes all voluntary <hi>Seruices</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15581:5"/>what apparance or outward ſhew of <hi>deuotion</hi> ſoeuer they beare.</p>
            <p>By which and other like places, I was moued to examine my <hi>profeſsion</hi> whether it were of Gods inſtitution, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall command ſpecified to vs, or whether <hi>God</hi> were the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of thoſe <hi>Seruices</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> which now beate great ſway in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and after due examination I found out for certaine that many points of the <hi>Religion,</hi> now embraced by the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> are not to be found within the volume of Gods Word. When I conſidered this, and perceiued the weakenes of the grounds that muſt warrant our <hi>ſoules,</hi> it gaue me occaſion to forſake my communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in whoſe boſome I haue beene long detayned; of whom I may iuſtly complaine as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> did of the falſe <hi>teachers</hi> in his dayes, they haue reiected the Word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and what wiſedome is then in them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe I often buſied my ſelfe in reading of <hi>Books,</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp; ſuch as handled matters now in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie: as the <hi>Apollogy</hi> of the moſt reuerent <hi>Father</hi> and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Scholler <hi>Iohn Iewell,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sariſbury,</hi> written againſt a friend and neere Kiſeman of mine Docter <hi>Harding;</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with another no leſſe reuerent then learned, <hi>Marcus Antoniuus de dominis</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> whom after I had well peruſed, I found ſuch comfort in my conſcience and ſuch ſollid doctrine for my <hi>ſoule,</hi> that I made no doubt to ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, a domino factum eſt hoc,</hi> this is the Lords doing. Now the Sunne is vp, and the Clouds of ignorance are gone, the truth ſhineth, and the Kingdome of Heauen is at hand, therfore I may ſay with my Text, <hi>bonum eſt mihi quia humiliaſtime.</hi> It is good for mee that I was in trouble, for thereby I haue learned thy Statutes. But what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15581:5"/>are theſe <hi>Statutes?</hi> they are the Word of God, contayned in the Law and the Prophets: which are the rule of our Life, and the ſquare of our Faith, and the very Oracle of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, from Heauen to reueale his <hi>will</hi> vnto vs, for certaine it is that Chriſt came not to deſtroy the <hi>Law,</hi> but to fulfill it: hee ſwarued not from the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, neither did the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> teach any thing vpon their owne will and diſcretion, but the Doctrine which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of Chriſt, they faithfully deliuered it vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Nations.</p>
            <p>And this they preached at the firſt in <hi>viua voce:,</hi> that is, in a liuely Voyce, and afterward deliuered it vnto vs in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to be the foundation and Pillar of our Faith, <hi>Qui hoc credit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) nihil habet quod vitra credat:</hi> He that beleeueth this, hath no Obligation to beleeue any thing elſe: and this is that which we ought to beleeue without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adding or diminiſhing.</p>
            <p>I would now demand of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Papalins,</hi> in what <hi>Goſpell,</hi> in what <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> in what <hi>Prophet</hi> or <hi>Euangeliſt,</hi> or Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> they find either Pope or his ſupremacy? where are his Pardons? where is his Maſſe? where Images? together with many other his Fopperies, which now they hold to be very precious. We reade in the 20. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> that almighty God doth expreſly forbid the making of any <hi>Image,</hi> to repreſent the Perſon of Almighty God, or to do any ſeruice and obey ſance to any <hi>Picture,</hi> or repreſentation of the creature: for firſt God is a Spirit inviſible, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and Eternall, and therefore hee cannot be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by any Image or creature, which is both corporall and momentary, and therefore God in his ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement forbiddeth all ſeruice done vnto Images: but contrary vnto this the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth command
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15581:6"/>and allow not only the making of Images, but alſo doth command the ſeruing and worſhipping of them, as by incenſing them, in lighting of Candles vnto them, by kneeling before them, and by yeelding vp their offrings, and deuotions vnto them.</p>
            <p>All which can bee no leſſe then groſſe Idolatry: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, they do not worſhip their Images, as <hi>ſtocks</hi> and <hi>ſtones,</hi> but as they repreſent either God or ſome Saint: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe did not the <hi>Iſralits,</hi> worſhip their golden Calfe, as the true God, but they did worſhip the true God in the Calfe, and yet notwithſtanding, the Text ſaith, that they did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Idolatry, and many of them were ſeuerely puniſhed for the ſame, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. ſo that the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is as groſſe as that of the <hi>Iſralites.</hi> What can bee more iniutious vnto God then to hope for helpe of him, and yet notwithſtanding to pray vnto a ſenceleſſe ſtock? The faith of the Patriarkes and Prophets, &amp; righteous Fathers from the beginning of the world, was the ſame as ours is, and ought to be, as the Apoſtle ſaith, that they were all bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in the red Sea, and did eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and iniutious vnto drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke, as wee doe now: But was <hi>Abraham, Iſaack,</hi> or <hi>Iaacob,</hi> Papiſts? did they fall downe before ſtocks and ſtones? before Idols or Images to pray or offer vnto them? did they go on pilgrimage one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Relikes to doe deuotion vnto them? there is neither ſhew nor ſhadow of theſe things in the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt, <hi>nee diſceſsit a lege neque a Prophetis:</hi> but none of all this is to bee found in the Law or the Prophets, therefore in no wiſe to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>As touching the diſtinction which they vſe betwixt <hi>Duleiam</hi> and <hi>Latreiam,</hi> affirming that they giue to Saints
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15581:6"/>onely <hi>Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iam;</hi> that is, a kind of Religious Seruice, and that they giue <hi>Latreiam</hi> vnto Almighty God, intimating thereby that they both worſhip God and ſerue their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: Our Sauiour confoundeth them in the 4, of <hi>Mathew</hi> ſaying as is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> perſwadeth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to turne from Idols and Images, and to ſerue the euerliuing God, where hee doth vſe the word <hi>Duliea,</hi> for the Seruice of the true God, ſhewing heereby the oppoſition that is betwixt the one and the other, that he that ſerueth Images, cannot in any wiſe ſerue the Almighty God:yea God himſelf ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it plainely, in his firſt Commandement, to worſhip and ſerue him, only, neither will he giue his Honour to any other.</p>
            <p>In the firſt precept God condemneth all falſe Gods, in the ſecond all falſe worſhiping, of the true God, as making of Images vnto God, or yeelding vnto the Image any part of deuotion which belongeth vnto the Lord. For it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know the true God, and to acknowledge him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to be worſhipped, according to the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; yet breake the 2. by worſhipping him amiſſe: As in ſetting vp of Images, and bowing and kneeling vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for as the Almighty God ſaith in the 27. of <hi>Deut.</hi> verſe 15 <hi>Curſed be the man that ſhall make any carued or molten Image, for it is abomination vnto the Lord, they that make them are like vnto them, and ſo are all they that put their truſt in them.</hi> For as <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> the ſonnes of <hi>Aaron</hi> by offring of ſtrange fire before the Lord, became lyable to his wrath and maledictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſo the <hi>Papiſts</hi> that doe adde ſtrange doctrines and new inuented traditions to the Word of God,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15581:7"/>and ſeruice of the Lord do incurre his heauy wrath &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall diſpleaſure. And therfore we are willed by the holy Ghoſt to flye from them and their abhominations, leaſt we be partakers of their ſinne, end ſo likewiſe of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</p>
            <p>The 2. <hi>Motiue</hi> that moued me to leaue the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do as it were hood-winke the people in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, giuing a <hi>Seruice</hi> in a language they vnderſtand not, amazing them with many outward Ornaments, and huge heapes of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> calling <hi>Ignorance</hi> the the Mother of Deuotion, and <hi>Images</hi> Layemens Books. But we reade in the Councell of <hi>Tolledo</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> that <hi>Ignorantia eſt mater omnium errorum,</hi> Ignorance is the mother of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> but rather of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and the roote of all errour. What ſhould it auaile <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſpeake in Hehrew to a man of <hi>Africa,</hi> who vnderſtands no Hebrew, and what may it auaile the people of other countries to heare their common Seruice in a tongue they vnderſtand not: for albeit they heare with their eares, they vnderſtand not with their hearts, they are not much better then Birds and Parrats which babble much, and vnderſtand nothing: Therefore in the primatiue Church; when Faith was then in learning, the prayers &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Seruice was ſet fourth in a common tongue, knowne vnto the people that they might vnderſtand what they did profeſſe, and to be able to giue a reaſon of their faith.</p>
            <p>When Almighty God appointed <hi>Moſes</hi> to open the Law for the direction of his Church, he decreed it as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting duty to all his people, that the booke of the <hi>Law</hi> ſhold not depart out of their mouthes, but that they ſhould meditate therein day and night, to obſerue and doe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all that is written: But how ſhould they meditate in them if they be vnknown to them? and how ſhould they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15581:7"/>know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they be in a tongue they vnderſtand not? is not this the curſe which God by his Prophet denounceth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I wil ſpeak vnto this people in another language &amp; by ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lips, ſo as they ſhal not vnderſtand me:</hi> who would not iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſpect ſuch a church, yea &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to maintain and continue their errour, they will haue none of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple either to ſearch the Scriptures, or to vnderſtand their common Seruice that they heare dayly? Thus the ſilly <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palins</hi> are led like blinde men they know not whether, and with her <hi>fides implicita</hi> that is, to beleeue in groſſe (for their part) they know not what are lamentably ſeduced. The people go to ſee Maſſe, but not to vnderſtand it; and oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Prieſt himſelfe vnderſtands not what he ſaith, and this is done for a double end, the one is that the people may be kept ſtill in Ignorance, and the other is, that it may bee a marke of the <hi>Popes</hi> dominion, in that they vſe his language in their deuine Seruice, and ſo might bee thought to hold their Religion from the <hi>Popes</hi> Chaire, euen as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> conſtreyneth the <hi>Indians</hi> to ſpeake <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> the better to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them vnder his Dominion. But the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86. <hi>Dominus narauit in Scriptur is populoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> God hath opened and declared his wayes and will in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but in whoſe Scriptures? <hi>Hierom</hi> vpon this place an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth thus, the Scriptures of the people, ſo called, becauſe they be read vnto the people, that is to ſay, that all may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, becauſe the Princes of Chriſt which were the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Euangeliſts did not write them for afew, but for the whole people, not that afew, but that all ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writ long Epiſtles to the <hi>Corinthians, Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Philippians,</hi> in his owne language, that all might reade and vnderſtand what hee wrote vnto them: Why
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15581:8"/>then may not others reade the ſame Epiſtles in their own language as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Epheſians</hi> did in theirs. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Laeta,</hi> writeth thus, Let thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter loue diuine and heauenly Bookes inſtead of ſilkes and precious Stones, let her learne of the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> to deſpiſe earthly things, let the Prouerbs of <hi>Salomon</hi> teach her to liue vertuouſly, let the <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> accuſtome her to renounce worldly vanity, let <hi>Iob</hi> teach her patience, let her take the Goſpell of Chriſt into her hands, &amp; let it not depart from her, let her diligently ſtudy the Acts and Epiſtles of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And when ſhee hath enriched the Cloſſet of her heart with ſuch riches, then let her learne the doctrine of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and the bookes of <hi>Moſes.</hi> This was the practice and vſe of the Church in Saint <hi>Hieromes</hi> time, and long after him, as may appeare by Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> in his Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis.</p>
            <p>If the reading of the Scriptures may bee forbidden becauſe ſome abuſe them; in the vſing: then alſo may the Sacraments be forbidden, becauſe they are ſometimes abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the receiuing, which to doe were a thing much diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Gods will &amp; pernicious vnto his Church: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the propoſing their ſeruice in a ſtrange language, and forbidding the people the reading of the Scriptures, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together againſt Gods word &amp; the ancient cuſtome of the Primatiue Church, and ſo by conſequence is not to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by any of the children of the Church of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>A third reaſon that moued me to follow this pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution was, that they hold againſt all Scripture, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall reaſon Purgatory, that is, a purging fire after this life to clenſe our ſins. Againſt this opinion of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> our Sauiour himſelfe in the 16. of Saint <hi>Luke</hi> doth much
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15581:8"/>confute, where he maketh mention only of 2. places; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Heauen and Hell: ſaying, that the rich mans ſoule pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after death went to Hell and there was tormented; and <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſoule, at his death, was carried by the Angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, a place of ioy and comfort. For as Saint <hi>Ciprian</hi> ſaith againſt <hi>Demetrian,</hi> that after this life there is no place of Repentance, there is no ſatisfaction more to be made, life is heere either loſt or won by the due worſhipping of God, and the fruits of faith; So the ſame Author ſaith in the ſame Treatiſe, that if a man in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting hence doth ſincerely acknowledge his ſinnes, and truly imbrace Gods Word, thus confeſſing, and thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, he hath free pardon and forgiueneſſe granted him of all his ſinnes, by Gods goodneſſe and free mercy, and at that very inſtant paſſeth to immortality: Euen in the laſt moment of his life God refuſeth not <hi>Repentance,</hi> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is truely done, is not to late done.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Booke <hi>Debono Mortis</hi> ſaith, that he that in this life receiueth not remiſſion of his ſinnes, ſhall not haue remiſſion in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Now if their ſinnes be forgiuen in this world, likewiſe the puniſhment due to the ſame is alſo forgiuen in this world, and ſo there can remaine no Purgatorie to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them in the next life. But certaine it is, that the bloud of Chriſt doth clenſe vs from all our ſinnes, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, and is the onely Purgatory, that a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man ſhould hold, which doth deliuer his people as well from the puniſhment due to ſins, as from the ſinne it ſelfe: for as the Prophes <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, our puniſhment was laid vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and with his ſtripes wee are healed. Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi> in his Sermon <hi>De tempore</hi> 232. ſaith, there are but 2. places, hee that reigneth not with Chriſt at his departure
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15581:9"/>hence ſhall periſh with the Diuell without end, ſo that in what ſtare the laſt day of our life ſhall find vs, in the ſame ſtate the laſt day of our life ſhall iudge vs.</p>
            <p>Now if this be true, as moſt true it is, then the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Maſſe ſo much eſteemed in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſeruice, is but a forgery: For firſt it cannot be propitiatory for the dead: <hi>for as the Tree falleth ſo it lyeth,</hi> and as man is found in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, ſo goeth he to Hell or to Heauen. A third place is not mentioned, now if any be in Heauen, <hi>Maſſes</hi> cannot auaile them, for they enjoy all bliſſe poſſibly already, if they be in Hell, we read, <hi>ab inferno non eſt redemptio,</hi> out of Hell there is no redemption, for as the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>a man can by no means redeeme his brother, he cannot pay his ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to God, ſo precious is the redemption of ſoules, and the continuance for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo it is cleare, that for the dead it cannot be propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory, and as for the liuing it cannot benefite them, for then were it derogatory to the Paſſion of Chriſt once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all vpon the Croſſe: whoſe Oblation was abſolute and perfect as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the 5. to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 6.7. ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, and therefore needeth not <hi>Maſſe,</hi> or any thing elſe to helpe it, yea it were groſſe and damnable to ſuppoſe any imperfection in that Sacrifice and Oblation of our Sauiour once offred on the Croſſe, ſeeing that God the Father twiſe ſpake from Heauen with a loud voyce, ſaying <hi>this is my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Reaſon, that moued mee to renounce my former profeſſion with the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> is that, they quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the words of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> and the whole vſe of the ancient Chriſtians abuſe the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, partly by adding, and partly by diminiſhing, from the ſame, when our Sauiour ſpake theſe words, <hi>hoc eſt corpus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15581:9"/>meum:</hi> This is my Body, hee expounded himſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſaying, it is the <hi>Spirit</hi> that giueth life, the <hi>Fleſh</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing. Theſe words are ſpoken ſpiritually, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt vnderſtand them ſpiritually. Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in his Commentaries vpon the 98. <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſaith, you ſhall not eate this Body that you ſee, neither ſhall you drinke that Bloud which vpon the Croſſe was once ſhed: for our Sauior recommended vnto vs a Sacrament (to wit) that which you ſee on the Table is Bread, and that which you ſee in the Cup is wine, but touching that wherein your faith is to be inſtructed, is the Body and Bloud of Chriſt For as Baptiſme doth change a man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to grace, yet notwithſtanding he remaines the ſelfeſame man according to viſible meaſure as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but inuiſibly by grace is made another man; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly nothing is added, but inwardly all is changed: So in the bleſſed Sacrament, outwardly nothing is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but there remaineth true Bread and true Wine, but inwardly by faith, we apprehend the Body and Bloud of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But theſe words which our Sauiour ſpake figuratiuely, the Papiſts expounds them literally, and thereby they cauſe the people to commit Idolatry, by adoring Bread as God: for they hold that after the words of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there remaineth no longer Bread nor Wine, but there is really and Tranſubſtantially the Body and Bloud of Chriſt. But Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that the Heauens muſt containe the Body of Chriſt vntill the end of the World.</p>
            <p>Now if Chriſts Body bee in Heauen; then it cannot bee in the Earth at once, and the ſame time: for as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15581:10"/>Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Tractatu 3. in Iohannem. Corpus Domini in quo reſurrexit, vno tantum in loco eſſe poteſt.</hi> If they ſay that it is done by miracle in the Sacrament, then it ſhould be viſible, to the outward eye and ſences. When Chriſt turned water into Wine, it was viſible Wine. When <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod was turned into a Serpent, it was a viſible Serpent, and ſo if the Bread be turned into the Body, and the Wine into the Bloud of Chriſt, it muſt alſo be a viſible body.</p>
            <p>But if they expound theſe words of our Sauiour, <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum</hi> literally, to belong vnto all, why ſhould they not alſo expound the words following literally, that when he tooke the Cup, he ſaid, <hi>This is my bloud,</hi> ſhould be appertayning to all aſwel as the Bread. In the old Law Circumciſion was called the Lords Couenant, when it was not the Couenant but a Signe thereof: For the Couenant was this to <hi>Abraham: Ego ero Deus tuus &amp; Deus ſeminis tui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Paſcall <hi>Lambe</hi> was called the <hi>Paſſeouer</hi> of the Lord, when it was but the ſigne of the Paſſeouer, as paſſing ouer the red Sea, ſo that it may ſtand with good Reaſon, that Chriſt called the Bread his Body, as hee called the Paſcall Lambe his Paſſeouer, and yet was but a ſigne thereof, ſo the Bread is called his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and is but a ſigne or remembrance of the ſame: and therefore it is called a Sacrament becauſe that in it one thing is ſeene, and another thing vnderſtood that which is ſeene is Bread, and Wine, and hath a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble apparance or forme, but that which is vnderſtood hath a ſpirituall vſe and profit.</p>
            <p>So that the thing which ſignifieth, is oft-times called
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15581:10"/>by the name of the thing which it ſignifieth, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth the Rocke Chriſt, yet it was not Chriſt by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but by ſignification; euen ſo our Sauiour ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> when he gaue Bread the ſigue of his Body, and the Apoſtle ſaid, the Rock was Chriſt, for that the Rocke which they ſpake of ſignified Chriſt. The Goſpell ſtandeth not in the words of the Scripture but in the meaning.</p>
            <p>Therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that the Communicant doth eate Bread after Conſecration; for if the Bread were who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly Tranſubſtantiated into the Body of Chriſt, hence it followeth that euery one that doth receiue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament doth alſo eate the Body of Chriſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently cannot be damned. For our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>He that eateth my Fleſh, and drinketh my Bloud hath eternall life:</hi> &amp; ſo by this rule the wicked ſhall be ſaued as well as the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Moreouer if Chriſt be preſent according to his humane Nature, then is it no Sacrament: for euery Sacrament is a ſigne, &amp; <hi>inanis eſt ſigni viſus vbi resipſa preſens eſt</hi> the ſigne is to no effect, where the thing it ſelfe is preſent. And it is to be noted likewiſe, that the ſigne muſt haue ſome Analogie with the thing that it ſignifieth: Now the thing ſignified is the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, which is true meate &amp; true drinke, as our Sauiour himſelfe witneſſeth, in St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, but the <hi>ſpecies</hi> or accidents of Bread and Wine are not true meate, nor true drinke, &amp; by that meanes cannot giue any fit proportion with the thing ſignified by them. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is an Axiome in Phyloſophy, that <hi>accidentis eſſe eſt in eſſe,</hi> that the being of an accident is to be in ſome ſubiect. But theſe accidents as colour, ſauour and roundneſſe, they cannot bee in any ſubiect and ſo by conſequence they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not exiſt in the Sacrament.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15581:11"/>
            <p> For they cannot be in the body of Chriſt becauſe it is glorified: but the accidents are ſubiect to corruption; and therfore they muſt either exiſt without a ſubiect, which is contrary to <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> or elſe to bee ſeated in the Body of Chriſt which is now glorified, and this is impoſſible. It is further to be noted that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and curtall this Sacrament, for they take the bloud of our Sauiour (which is our redemption) from the lay-peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: yet certaine it is that our Sauiour did inſtitute this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament vnder both kinds, and as he ſaid to all, take &amp; eate, this is my Body: So did he likewiſe ſpeake vnto all, when he deliuered the <hi>Cup;</hi> ſaying, <hi>drinke ye all of this?</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſayth, <hi>As often as ye eate of this Bread, and drinke of this Cup, ye ſhew forth the Lords death vntill he come</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hailes</hi> ſaith, whole Chriſt is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned vnder each kind, but the Fleſh only vnder the forme of Bread, and the Bloud vnder the forme of Wine. And heere vpon <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> Pope, made a Decree that they ſhould either receiue the whole vnder both kinds, or receiue none at all vnder any kinde: For there can bee no deuiſion of this one Sacrament and high miſtery, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Sacriledge; ſo that by their owne Doctors it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident that they commit great Sacriledge in deuiding this Sacrament, and do much abuſe the people of God in deceiuing them of the precious Bloud of our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>The 5. <hi>Motiue</hi> which mooued mee to perſiſt in this my enterpriſe, is, that the <hi>Pope</hi> challengeth authority vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to forgiue ſinnes, and thereupon ſendeth forth his Bulls, Pardons, and Indulgences, pardoning whom he liſt, and as he liſt, as if he were God himſelfe, hauing abſolute
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15581:11"/>power to do what he liſt, inſomuch as Traytors and Rebels againſt God and their lawfull Prince, hee will not only par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don without exception, but he will enable them in their damnable courſes, to the ouerthrowing of themſelues and their Princes. What the Religion of <hi>Rome</hi> is, it may eaſily appeare by this, that a man may haue for money a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,</hi> or diſpenſation for any ſinne, a <hi>Popes</hi> pardon is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for all: but to what end ſerueth pardons, when as there is no Purgatorie? for neither the ancient Fathers make mention of it, and the <hi>Grecians</hi> vntill this day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it not. <hi>Silueſter Prierias</hi> in his Booke againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> ſaith, that Pardons are not knowne vnto vs by any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scriptures, but by authorie of the Pope, which is greater then the authority of the Scriptures: <hi>Vox bouis non hominis.</hi> It is the voice or ſaying of ſome Beaſt, and not of any Chriſtian man.</p>
            <p>Certaine I am that the Pope cannot juſtifie an vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man whom God abhorreth, neither can he condemn the faithfull who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God doth much tender and fauour: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Pardons are rather pernitious then any whit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious to the perſons that buy them, bearing them in peace and ſecurity, when indeede they are in much perill and miſery.</p>
            <p>VVhere doe they find that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath any ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ouer Kings, Princes, or Emperours; that hee hath any authority to depoſe them from their Crownes, and dignities, and to abſolue their ſubiects from their Oath and Allegeance which they haue ſworne vnto their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: That vpon his Excommunication it is lawfull for them to rebell againſt them, and ſo practiſe all Hoſtility to depoſe them?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15581:12"/>
            <p> There is not one word ſentence or place out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to proue it; no precept or example of antiquity to warrant it, and yet they commend it for a chiefe point and ground of Catholike and Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>By what right doth he claime this ſupreme authority: if he clayme it as a ſucceſſor of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> it is impoſſible, for that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> neuer had any ſuch Title or preeminence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>It is true that Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Peter, Thou art Peter, and vpon this Rock I wil build my Church.</hi> Theſe words hitherto giue no ſuperiority to <hi>Peter</hi> aboue the reſt. Only they ſhew that the Church is built <hi>non ſuper petrum ſed ſuper Petram,</hi> not vpon the perſon of <hi>Peter</hi> but vpon the Rocke: Of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Petra autem erat Chriſtus,</hi> the Rock was Chriſt, whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſed to be the Sonne of the euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</p>
            <p>This confeſſion of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is, that Chriſt is the Rock wherevpon the Church is builded, <hi>aliud fundamentum nemo, poteſt ponere niſi id quod poſitum eſt Chriſtus Ieſus.</hi> Other Foundation can no man lay, but that which is laid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: namely, Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Where then ſhall wee find that <hi>Peter</hi> was made Prince of the Apoſtles, to rule ouer all the reſt, as our Popes doe now?</p>
            <p>But what hath the Pope to doe with <hi>Peter?</hi> or what doth the Pope doe as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did? Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did conuert ſoules, plant Churches, and preach the Word of God vnto all Nations, but in what Pulpit hath our Popes euer ſet foote? where haue they preached the Goſpell or expounded the Word.</p>
            <p>The firſt Leſſon that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth vs, is to feare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15581:12"/>God, the next is, to Honour the King. <hi>Quis haec eſt voluntas Dei,</hi> for this is the will of God. But the Popes ſay, that they are Princes aboue Nations and Kingdomes: they can depoſe Kings, and pull downe Emperours, they haue authority ouer their ſubiects, to diſcharge them from their Oathes, they haue the right and clayme vnto both ſwords, as well temporall as ſpirituall: And that all Kings and Princes ought to depend at their beck, and to ſweare obedience, vnto their holineſſe, as to their ſupreame heads and Soueraignes, vnder the paine and loſſe of all their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.</p>
            <p>We reade that <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight becauſe he could not haue the treaſury of <hi>France,</hi> at his command, endeauoured by all meanes poſſible to remoue <hi>Phillip</hi> the French King from his eſtate, and vnder his Bulls and Letters Pattents, made a deede of gift of all the ſtate of <hi>France</hi> vnto <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> then King of the Romans.</p>
            <p>As touching the Kings of this our Realme of England: as our duty and alleageance bindeth vs, we may iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3. by violence and tyrran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forced King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond to ſurrender vp his Crowne Imperiall into his Legats hands, and afterward for a certaine ſpace to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent him in priuate eſtate, to the great indignation and griefe of his louing ſubiects. Like wiſe that <hi>Innocentius</hi> the 3. ſtirred vp the Nobles and Commons of this Realme againſt King <hi>Iohn,</hi> and gaue the inheritance &amp; poſſeſſion of all his Dominions vnto <hi>Ludeuicus</hi> the French King, <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> of late dayes gaue away his Kingdome to <hi>Philip</hi> the 2. King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> Shall any one thinke that theſe be deeds of holines, and that he doth all this by right and equity through vertue of his ſpirituall priuiledge.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15581:13"/>
            <p> Surely no, it is meere ſacriledge againſt God, and tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny ouer his Princes and Vice-gerents, and not the part of any Miniſter of Chriſt or ſucceſſor of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>For firſt Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>that his Kingdome is not of this world.</hi> He himſelfe likewiſe refuſed to be made a King. He himſelfe payd tribute vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and commanded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do the ſame, ſaying, <hi>giue vnto Caeſar thoſe things that bee Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if Chriſt himſelfe was ſubiect vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all others to be ſubiect and obedient vnto him, it is a ſhame for the Byſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to exalt himſelfe aboue <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to animate others againſt him. <hi>Imperium in Principe &amp; obedientia in ſubdito, eſt de inre diuino,</hi> Rule in the Prince, and obedience in the Subiect, are both immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly from God; and as euery member of the body naturall muſt ſubiect it ſelfe vnto the rule and regiment of the head if it meane to liue and thriue: So muſt euery ſubiect in the body politicke, be ſubiect and gouerned by the Prince which is the head of all, and aboue all. And therefore they are called in the <hi>Pſalmes Voseſtis Dij,</hi> yee are as Gods, ſo that he which contemneth them, contemneth God; they are called nourſing Fathers, that we ſhould alwayes loue and reuerence them like vnto our Fathers; they are alſo called Kings Princes and Rulers of the Earth, which are Names and Titles of honour, ſo that thoſe whom God vouchſafeth thus to Honour, we ought without all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, to loue, honour, and obey. Therefore euery ſoule that is ſubiect to God muſt bee ſubiect to them, becauſe he that calleth them Kings calleth vs ſubiects: this is their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that God hath choſen them Kings, and ſet them vpon the Throne to rule his people, and hath commanded euery
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15581:13"/>ſoule to be ſubiect vnto their power <hi>Si omnis anima,</hi> if eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule muſt be ſubiect vnto their power, then doubtleſſe muſt both Popes and Byſhops bee ſubiect to their Prince: <hi>Qui vos tentat ab hac vniuer ſalitate excipere conatur decipere.</hi> He that goeth about to exempt you from this vniuerſall Law, goeth about to beguile you. For our Sauiour as hee commanded it, ſo did hee in his owne perſon performe it. <hi>Exemplum dedit vobis vt ſicut ipſe fecit &amp; vos faciatis:</hi> Hee left you an example that as hee did, ſo ſhould you alſo doe.</p>
            <p>So that it is a thing moſt certaine that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no authority ouer Kings either in Eccleſiaſticall or Temporall matters, but is therein an Vſurper, Intruder, and a moſt odious Traytor, both to God and Prince: for all the ancient Churches haue affirmed, and euer acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the ſupreame auhority of Princes, aboue all Prieſts and people whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> an ancient Doctor and Prieſt, in his Booke <hi>ad Scapulam,</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>Colimus Imperatorem vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem a Deo ſecundum &amp; ſoli Deo minorem:</hi> Wee honour the Prince as next and imediatly vnto God, &amp; inferior only vnto God. And in his Apologeticks, he ſaith, that <hi>Principes ſunt a Deo ſecundi poſt eum primi ante omnes &amp; ſuper omnes:</hi> That Kings and Princes are the ſecond to God, next vnto God, aboue all and ouer all. <hi>Optatus lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Contra Parmenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> ſaith, that <hi>ſupra Imperatorem non eſt niſi ſolus Deus qui fecit Imperatorem.</hi> It was the Lord which appointed <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Ioſua, Dauid</hi> and his poſterity to rule ouer <hi>Iſrael,</hi> It was the Lord which moued the peoples heart to feare honour and obey them, for as euery beame is from the Sunne, and euery Branch is from the Roote, ſo doth euery power pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15581:14"/>from God, ſo that it is <hi>Deiure deuino,</hi> that Kings haue rule ouer their ſubiects, and therefore all ſubiects by the Law of God and nature are bound to honour and obey their Princes.</p>
            <p>Good Kings are Gods Images, and euill Princes are his Executioners: <hi>Aſher,</hi> was his Rod; <hi>Nabuchadonezer,</hi> his ſeruant; and <hi>Cyrus,</hi> was his anoynted: And therefore aibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it God vſeth them as a Father doth his rod, firſt to correct his children by them, and then breaketh and throweth them away, yet the children and beloued of the Lord muſt ſubmit themſelues vnder his inſtrument of correction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rubenites, Gaddits,</hi> and halfe the Tribe of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſaid to <hi>Salomon, whoſoeuer ſhall reſiſt thy will, or will not obey whatſoeuer thou commandeſt, let him bee put to death.</hi> So that in <hi>Iſrael</hi> whether their Kings were faithfull or vngodly, the people euer yeelded ciuill faith and obedience. For as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, this is the will of God, and whoſoeuer reſiſteth this obedience, reſiſteth the will of God, and ſo heapeth vnto himſelfe vengeance againſt the day of wrath: and ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently this doctrine of rebelling againſt Princes muſt needs be very damnable and odious, and worthy to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned of all thoſe that feare God. But it is not my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe or intent to ſet downe heere in particular all the erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious parts of Doctrine at this preſent profeſſed and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for there are many other points &amp; pernicious grounds by me obſerued, which in no point agreeth with the word of God, but I ſuppoſe that theſe few poſitions which I haue already touched may bee ſufficient enough to make it manifeſt vnto the world that I haue enterpriſed nothing without good reaſon; &amp; that my conſcience could neuer haue ſuffered mee to haue liued in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15581:14"/>quiet and reſt, if I had done any otherwiſe: all which things duly and carefully ballanced in my mind, haue exceedingly ſtirred me vp to this my pious reſolution.</p>
            <p>It is a difficult thing to reſiſt Gods voice, to fight againſt the truth; which diſcouereth her ſelfe ſo apparantly; my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſtill vrging me, I could doe no leſſe then retire my ſelfe back vnto the Lord, from whom I haue long erred &amp; gone aſtray, ſaying as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Socrates</hi> is my friend, &amp; ſo is <hi>Plato</hi> my friend, but the friendſhip of the truth is far aboue all. I can no longer beare witneſſe againſt God, it is no longer ſecure, to call good euill, or euill good, light darkeneſſe, or darkeneſſe light. I muſt not be aſhamed of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, for it is the mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God vnto ſaluation: It is now high time to ſet aſide all blinde affection, and to iudge vprightly. It is dangerous to ioyne with them that haue burnt Gods Word; and ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called it a leaden rule, &amp; a Noſe made of waxe, that call ignorance the mother of Deuotion, &amp; dumb Images Lay mens Bookes, who forbid marriage, and lycence Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines, who haue deuiſed vnto themſelues a ſtrange Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, contrary to the Scriptures, ancient Counſels, old doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and example of the Primatiue Church: whom ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdomes, countries and infinite thouſands of godly people haue forſaken: From whom the holy Ghoſt by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words hath commanded vs to depart: as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>Apocalips,</hi> Come away from her O my people that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes, leſt ye be alſo parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of her plagues: for ſhe hath falſified the holy farthers with ſuch tranſlations and expoſitions, not as may beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe their meanings, but as may beſt further their owne pretenſes, and purpoſes, they wreſt them, they alter them,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15581:15"/>they put to them, and take from them: ſometimes they take the bare words againſt the meaning, and ſometimes they frame a meaning againſt the words: they imagine counſels that were neuer lied, <hi>Canons</hi> of counſels that were neuer ſeene, they bring forged Pamphlets vnder the name of <hi>Athanaſius. Anacletus,</hi> and other godly Fathers by whom they were neuer made. Theſe are not errors in manners which may be in any good Church, but they are errors in Faith and Doctrine, which cannot ſtand with the true Church. And therefore as Saint <hi>Ciprian</hi> ſaith, let not lies deceiue vs any longer, it is night vntill the day ſpring, but when the Day appeareth, and the Sunne of truth is vp, both the darkeneſſe of the night, as alſo the thefts commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in darkeneſſe will appeare and giue place. Now the Sunne of truth is vp, and the Clouds of ignorance are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, I will ſay with Saint <hi>Paul, Let vs caſt away darkeneſſe, and put on the armour of light:</hi> To maintaine a fault knowne, is a double fault: Errour cannot ſtand but by errour, and the mouth that ſpeaketh vntruth killeth the ſoule. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may ſafely and ioyfully ſay, <hi>Bonum eſt mihi domine, quia humiliaſti me, vt diſcam inſtiſicationes tuas,</hi> It is good for me that I haue beene in trouble, for thereby I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thy truth.</p>
            <p>O my God leade, me in the truth, teach mee to do thy will. Albeit I haue erred and ſtrayed like a loſt ſheepe, <hi>Ego tamen filius tuus; &amp; fillius ancillae tuae,</hi> Yet I am as child of thine inheritance, and borne and brought vp of thy Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd, which is thy Church and Spouſe. Open mine eyes, &amp; ſuffer me not to be deceiued by the abuſes of the world: Sweete Ieſus confirme me in this my reſolution, helpe my vnbeliefe, increaſe the Faith which is within me; fructifie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15581:15"/>in me that aſſurance of <hi>Abraham</hi> who beleeued in hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hope: arme me with thy promiſes: deliuer me from mine enemines: repleniſh me with the Spirit of conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to the end, and in the end, that hauing gotten the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I may ſay with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Bonum certame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certaui, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruaui, curſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, conſummani, de reliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> repoſita eſt mihi coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na iuſtitiae quam reddit mihi in ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> die Iuſtus index.</hi> 2. Tim. 4.7.8. I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the Faith. 8. Henceforth there is laid vp for me a Crowne of Righteouſnes, which the Lord the righteous Iudge ſhall giue mee at that Day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
